How air conditioning works.
There are eight main components that
play a pivotal role in cooling your home.
A Thermostat
Condenser
Compressor
Fan
Metering Device
Evaporator
Blower
and a Filter.
The first step begins with setting your
thermostat to the desired temperature.
This triggers the condenser fan and
compressor to turn on.
The compressor begins pumping a fluid
called a 'refrigerant' throughout the system.
This is used because of its low boiling point.
Refrigerant constantly changes from a
vapor to a liquid in order to move heat from
inside your home to the outdoors.
It enters the compressor as a low-temperature, low-pressure vapor.
After it's compressed, it leaves as a high-temperature, high-pressure vapor.
It then travels through the condenser
coil, where the vapor condenses into a liquid.
The heat it has collected indoors and after compression, is released outside.
The fan inside the unit helps with this
process.
The refrigerant leaves the condenser as
a medium-temperature, high-pressure liquid.
Then, flows to the metering device.
In this case, a thermal expansion valve is used.
A pin inside the valve adjusts the flow rate of refrigerant
depending on the temperature at the
evaporator end, using a 'sensing bulb'.
As it flows through the valve, its
pressure drops significantly,
releasing a low-temperature, low-pressure liquid/vapor mix.
The lower pressure allows room
temperature air to boil the refrigerant.
The chilled refrigerant then flows
through the evaporator coil.
The blower begins circulating air
throughout the house.
Room-temperature air is pulled in through the return duct
and passes through the filter to remove particulates.
The heat from the air is absorbed into
the refrigerant inside the evaporator coil,
dispersing chilled air through the supply duct.
As the air passes over the coil,
the refrigerant is boiled and evaporates back into vapor form.
During this process, condensation forms on the outside of the coil
and exits through a condensate drain
line.
The refrigerant returns to the condenser
to disperse the collected heat outdoors,
and the cycle starts again.
Your home is slowly cooled,
and the thermostat shuts off the equipment
once it senses the desired temperature.